A Finding Aid to the Anne Goldthwaite Papers, 1910-1950, in the Archives of American Art AAA.goldanne
Archives of American Art
Anne Goldthwaite papers
1910-1950
AAA.goldanne
Archives of American Art
0.3 Linear feet
The papers of painter Anne Goldthwaite measure 0.3 linear feet and date from 1910 to 1950. Found within the papers are memoirs of Goldthwaite and her grandmother; clippings and exhibition catalogs; and photographs of Goldthwaite, her family and friends, and her work.
Goldthwaite, Anne, 1869-1944
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Anne Goldthwaite papers were donated by Lucy Goldthwaite in 1967 and a watercolor was donated by Ruth Anderson in 1982.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of this collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reel D359 at the Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the papers as described in this finding aid does not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm due to reprocessing.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Washington, D.C. office.
Biographical/Historical note
Painter and printmaker Anne Goldthwaite (1869-1944) lived and worked in Alabama and New York, New York. Goldthwaite was born in Montgomery, Alabama, spent her childhood in Dallas, Texas, and with the encouragement of family, moved to New York to pursue her art studies in 1892. There, she studied art with her mentor, Walter Shirlaw, at the National Academy of Design. In 1906, Goldthwaite traveled to Paris and became part of the circle of modern artists who founded the Académie Moderne. While her friends were exploring modernist styles, her style of painting remained figurative. She returned to America in 1913, and her work was selected for exhibition in the Armory Show.
From 1922 to 1944, Goldthwaite taught at the Art Students League and received private portrait commissions. During the summers, she would return to Montgomery, Alabama, which remained a rich source for her works of genre scenes of the south. Goldthwaite served as president of the New York Society of Women Artists from 1937-1938 and died in New York City in 1944.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter Anne Goldthwaite measure 0.3 linear feet and date from 1910 to 1950. Found within the papers are memoirs of Goldthwaite and her grandmother; clippings and exhibition catalogs; and photographs of Goldthwaite, her family and friends, and her work.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 1 series.
Series 1: Anne Goldthwaite papers, 1910-1950 (0.3 linear feet; Box 1, OV 2)
Painters--Alabama; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Painting, American; Photographs; Printmakers--Alabama; Printmakers--New York (State)--New York; Women artists
- Anne Goldthwaite Papers, 1910-1950; Series 1; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1, OV 2
  Scope and Contents note
  The Anne Goldthwaite papers consist of memoirs by Goldthwaite and her grandmother, Olivia; clippings and exhibition catalogs, including catalogs for one woman shows at the Downtown and MacBeth galleries in New York; and an undated watercolor by Goldthwaite. The series also includes photographs of Goldthwaite, her family and friends, and her work, including murals she completed as an artist working for the WPA in the 1930s.
  Arrangement note
  Materials are minimally arranged by document type.
  - Memoir, by Anne Goldthwaite, circa 1910-1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Memoir, by Olivia Goldthwaite, circa 1920-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Originally written in 1872.
  - Clippings, 1916-1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1920-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Artwork, Watercolor, circa 1925-1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Oversized material housed in OV 2.
  - Photographs of Anne Goldthwaite, circa 1910-1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of African Americans in Alabama, circa 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Self Portraits and Relatives, circa 1925-1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Women, circa 1925-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Men, circa 1925-1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Alabama and New York, circa 1925-1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Still Lifes and Animals, circa 1925-1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Photographs of Artwork, WPA Murals, circa 1925-1945 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photographs of Artwork, by Others, circa 1925-1945 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Oversized Watercolor from Box 1, Folder 5, circa 1925-1939 (Box OV 2)